<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>The trauellers ioy: or, A sermon on the third verse of the second chapter of Salomons song. By Master Iohn Adamson, minister of the Word of God at Liberton.</title>
            <author>Adamson, John, d. 1653.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1623</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 53 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 24 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2014-11">2014-11 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">B00218</idno>
            <idno type="STC">STC 143</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC S124444</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">52633073</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">ocm 52633073</idno>
            <idno type="VID">173894</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online text creation partnership.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. B00218)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 173894)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1475-1640 ; 2107:1)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>The trauellers ioy: or, A sermon on the third verse of the second chapter of Salomons song. By Master Iohn Adamson, minister of the Word of God at Liberton.</title>
                  <author>Adamson, John, d. 1653.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[8], 33, [6] p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed by Iohn Hauiland for Henry Bell.,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London, :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1623.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Dedication signed: A.S.</note>
                  <note>Headpieces, initials.</note>
                  <note>Signatures: A⁴ B-C⁸ D⁴.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in: Folger Shakespeare Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Bible. --  Bible. --  Song of Solomon II, 3 --  Sermons --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term>Sermons, English --  17th century.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2013-03</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-04</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-06</date>
            <label>Olivia Bottum</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-06</date>
            <label>Olivia Bottum</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2014-03</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:173894:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:173894:1"/>
            <p>
               <hi>The Trauellers ioy:</hi> OR, A SERMON on the third Verſe of the ſecond Chapter of <hi>Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lomons</hi> ſong.</p>
            <p>By Maſter IOHN ADAMSON, Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſter of the Word of God at <hi>Liberton.</hi>
            </p>
            <q>
               <bibl>CANT. 2.3.</bibl>
               <p>As the Apple tree among the trees of the wood, ſo is my welbeloued among the ſonnes of men: vnder his ſhadow I delighted and ſate downe, and his fruit was ſweet vnto my taſte.</p>
            </q>
            <p>LONDON, Printed by <hi>Iohn Hauiland</hi> for <hi>Henry Bell.</hi> 1623.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="dedication">
            <pb facs="tcp:173894:2"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:173894:2"/>
            <head>TO THE RIGHT VVorſhipfull, Sir <hi>Da<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uid Murray,</hi> Knight, all happi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe in this world, and in the world to come <hi>perpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tuall glory.</hi>
            </head>
            <opener>
               <salute>Worſhipfull Sir,</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">A</seg>S there is no vice more odi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous and deteſtable in the ſight of God, more hurtfull and pernicious to the Common<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wealth, and more repugnant and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trary to nature and reaſon, than ingra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>titude (that mother ſinne, or rather monſter of all miſchiefe) ſo there is no vertue more praiſe-worthy, more re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quiſite and more commendable in a Chriſtian than thankfulneſſe; that is, a
<pb facs="tcp:173894:3"/> requitall of one good turne with ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, a rendring (at leaſt a willing deſire to render, if meanes and ability faile) of one gift in lue and recompence of another; whereto the Prophet <hi>Dauid</hi> tieth the godly as to a duty which they muſt of neceſſity doe;<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Pſal.</hi> 33.1.</note> 
               <hi>It becom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>meth</hi> (ſaith hee) <hi>the vpright men to bee thankefull:</hi> and the Apoſtle <hi>Paul</hi> rec<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>koneth the vnthankfull amongſt the number of thoſe from whom wee ſhould turne away,<note place="margin">2. <hi>Tim.</hi> 3.2.</note> whoſe number (a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>las) in theſe perillous times increaſeth too faſt. Againſt the neglect of this precious Iewell the Lord himſelfe bit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terly enueigheth by his holy Prophet <hi>Eſaias,</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Eſa.</hi> 1.2, 3.</note> ſaying, <hi>I haue nouriſhed and brought vp children, and they haue rebel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led againſt me;</hi> yea he preferreth brute beaſts in the returne of their duty be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore them, ſaying, <hi>The Oxe knoweth his owner, and the Aſſe his maſters crib, but Iſrael knoweth not me.</hi> And our Saui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>our Chriſt hauing cured ten Lepers,
<pb facs="tcp:173894:3"/> and finding one onely thankfull, en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>couraging the one, he ſaith, <hi>Ariſe,</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Luk.</hi> 17.17, 19.</note> 
               <hi>goe thy way, thy faith hath made thee whole:</hi> and checking the others ingratitude, he ſaith, <hi>Where are the nine?</hi> The Gen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiles ſo worthily hated and abhor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red this vice, that they adiudged thoſe whom they found more willing to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceiue than willing to requite, execrable vnto God, iniurious to nature, and vnprofitable members of a common<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wealth, the which is cleere by the ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ample of <hi>Naaman,</hi> who being cleanſed of his leproſie,<note place="margin">2 <hi>Kin.</hi> 5.15.</note> 
               <hi>turned againe to the man of God,</hi> and would haue giuen him a reward, yea and would haue conſtrai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned him to receiue it: Finally this vice is ſo deteſtable to the very beaſts, that they ſtriue to ſhunne the foule impu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tation hereof, as <hi>Androdus</hi> his Lion (of which <hi>Gellius lib.</hi> 5, <hi>noct. attic. cap.</hi> 14. mentioneth) and <hi>Porus</hi> an Indian Kings Elephant (of which <hi>Eraſmus</hi> in the ſayings of <hi>Alexander</hi>) manifeſtly
<pb facs="tcp:173894:4"/> ſheweth. And ſurely, if it be ſo odi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous in Gods ſight, &amp; ſo deteſtable and hatefull to the Heathens and brute beaſts, what ſhould not Chriſtians doe to auoid and ſhun it? The conſidera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion hereof, together with your Wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhips fauour to my Vnkle being aliue, and earneſt care of his Orphane (his centuries) hee now being dead, and kindneſſe to mee (vnworthy thereof) ſince I came to this Country, hath em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>boldned, or rather conſtrained mee to dedicate this little Booke (albeit the talent of another mans zealous inuen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion) to your Worſhip (wherein is contained the miſerable eſtate of thoſe who are without Chriſt, and the ioy, eaſe, peace, contentment, and hap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pineſſe of thoſe who delight in him) humbly beſeeching your Worſhip to accept of my good will herein at this time, hoping if God permit, ere long to propine you with an increaſe, which in ſome meaſure ſhall bee pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>portionable
<pb facs="tcp:173894:4"/> to your ſowing. Thus ceaſing, I beſeech the Lord to conti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nue you in your godly courſe, and en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>due you with all bleſſings which ei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther this earth affordeth or Heauen containeth.</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>Your Worſhips moſt bounden, <hi>A. S.</hi>
               </signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="sermon">
            <pb facs="tcp:173894:5"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:173894:5"/>
            <head>THE TRAVEL<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>LERS IOY.</head>
            <epigraph>
               <q>
                  <bibl>CANT. 2.3.</bibl>
                  <p>As the Apple tree among the trees of the wood, ſo is my welbeloued among the ſonnes of men: vnder his ſhadow I delighted and ſate downe, and his fruit was ſweet vnto my taſte.</p>
               </q>
            </epigraph>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">I</seg>N the firſt Verſe the Bride<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>groome Chriſt praiſed his Bride, his Church, or the faithfull ſoule: Here ſhee praiſeth him, for none can praiſe him but they who haue béene before commended of him; and without controuerſie who are commended of him are praiſe-wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thy: So God accepteth no praiſe but of thoſe that are praiſe-worthy. Firſt the Lord beſtoweth grace vpon vs to make vs
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:173894:6"/> commendable, and then he praiſeth vs for his owne graces in vs, and all to this end, that we may reſolue our hearts, and open our mouthes in praiſe of his graci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous goodneſſe, as here doth the Church.</p>
            <p>The argument of her Lords commen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dation the Church taketh from his com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fortable fruits, which are firſt generally propounded, next particularly expoun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded. Propounded in compariſon, As is the Apple-trée of the Garden in reſpect of the trees of the foreſt, ſo is Chriſt my loue (ſaith the Church) in regard of other men: but the trées of the foreſt are naught in re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpect of the Apple-trée of the Garden: So are all other men in regard of Chriſt, they are naughty, barren, fruitleſſe and vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>profitable. This Propoſition firſt ſhew<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth vs a method how to meditate on Chriſt, that we may the better attaine to the knowledge of him. Would we ſée what excellency is in him? Let vs com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pare him with any thing beſide him. Things which ſimply looked on ſéeme to be moſt profitable, pleaſant, perfect, high, illuſtrious, glorious, compared with him, are baſe, imperfect, vnprofita<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble and naughty. As the moſt bright
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:173894:6"/> ſtarres of the Firmament vaniſh and diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>appeare in the ſight of the Sunne, ſo is the glory of all creatures eclipſed in his preſence. The Prophet <hi>Dauid</hi> to expreſſe his beauty compareth him with all other men, and ſaith:<note place="margin">Pſal. 45.2.7</note> He is <hi>fairer then the chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren of men:</hi> to expreſſe his vnction and gifts, he ſaith; He is <hi>anointed with the oyle of gladneſſe aboue his fellowes.</hi> So, if ye will know what a foode he is, com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pare him with Manna.<note place="margin">Pſal. 78 24.</note> Manna conſide<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red by it ſelfe, is called the Wheat of Heauen, and the Bread of Angels;<note place="margin">Ioh. 6.3<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
               </note> but in compariſon of him, the Lord denies it to be an heauenly Bread, it could not pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerue it ſelfe from ſtinke and rottenneſſe, much leſſe vs from death, where Chriſt the Bread of life doth both.<note place="margin">Ioh. 6.4<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>, 50.</note> Would we know what a Garment he is? compare him with the moſt excellent Garment. The Lillies of the field may contend with <hi>Salomons</hi> Roabe royall,<note place="margin">Mar. 6.29.</note> but no Garment may compare with Chriſt our wedding Garment.<note place="margin">Mat. 22.12. and Rom. 13.14.</note> Other Garments may defend vs from the iniury of the aire, may adorne vs and make vs beau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tifull in the eyes of men, may couer the blemiſhes of our bodies, but this Gar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:173894:7"/> being put on can defend vs from the ſtormy tempeſt of Gods wrath, can make vs beautifull, yea glorious in the eyes of God; and not onely couer, but cure the blemiſhes of our ſoules. There is no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing in this world profitable, pleaſant, commendable, high or glorious, whereby our Lord is not parabolically named in the Scripture, yet all being compared with him, all their excellency, greatneſſe and goodneſſe diſappeares, euaniſhes, and ſeemes nothing.</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">Rom. 1.19.</note>The vſe of this Doctrine is, not onely to lead vs by the hand of the creatures vnto the knowledge of Chriſt, but alſo to teach vs to diſcerne if we haue attained to the right knowledge of him, after wee haue knowne him, if we eſtéeme of any thing beſide him, we know him not as we ought to know him.<note place="margin">Phil. 3.7, 8.</note> Saint <hi>Paul</hi> accoun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted highly of many things before he knew Ieſus Chriſt, but after he had attained to the knowledge of him, he accounted them all to be dung, to be dammage, to be no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing. Secondly, obſerue what man is by nature and in himſelfe. He is as a barren and vnprofitable tree of the Wood:<note place="margin">Pſal. 14.2, 3</note> the Lord looked downe from Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uen
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:173894:7"/> vpon the children of men, to ſee if there were any that would vnderſtand and ſéeke God, but what findeth he after ſearch? all are gone out of the way, all are corrupt and become abominable, there is none that doth good, no not one.</p>
            <p>Howſoeuer the vnregenerate man pleaſe himſelfe, here is Gods Teſtimo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny of him: in reſpect of good he is vnpro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fitable, for he doth no good: in reſpect of euill hee is erronious, cloſe out of the way. And the reaſon of both his inepti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tude to the one and promptitude to the o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, is in himſelfe, for he is corrupt and ſtinketh.<note place="margin">Ioh. 15.4, 5.</note> A man out of Chriſt can bring forth no good fruit, without him we can doe nothing: hee may well produce the broad leaues of luſty and worldly wiſe words. He may ſpread the branches of his worldly glory to the ends of the earth; yea, and touch the Heauens with the top of his pride like <hi>Nebuchad-nezzar,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Dan. 4.8, 9, 17, 18, 19.</note> but in reſpect of good fruit all are as trées of the Wood, barren and vnprofitable. To this well agréeth Saint <hi>Iude,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Iude 12.</note> who deſcribing naturall men, in whom the ſupreme fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>culty is a naturall or reaſonable ſoule, they are, ſaith he, <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>,
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:173894:8"/> they are in reſpect of good <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, fruitleſſe trees, but in reſpect of euill they are <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, that is, trées of corrupt fruit, of corrupting fruit, or cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rupt in the harueſt. Their fruit is cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rupt in it ſelfe, and corrupteth others with its contagion, as rotten fruit cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rupteth the whole, as a little Leuen doth leuen the whole maſſe, and as a little gangrene in the fleſh corrupteth the whole body. Their fruits are as the Ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ples of Sodome, faire and pleaſant with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out, but cruſhed in péeces, are full of ſtinke and rottenneſſe: neither is their fruit only corrupt in reſpect of the inter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nall quality, and corrupting in reſpect of the externall operation, but alſo in re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gard of the ſeaſon, they are corrupt in the harueſt, when other trees are moſt abun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dant in good, bringing forth fruit for meat, and leaues for medicine, then are they moſt luxuriant in euill. O alas that there ſhould bee ſo many ſuch trées euen amongſt vs,<note place="margin">Luke 13.7.</note> in the midſt of the Orchard of God! while as other good Chriſtians are ſéeking the Lord, now when he offe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reth himſelfe to bee found in the Word and Sacraments, euen now in this har<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ueſt
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:173894:8"/> of grace, they are fruitleſſe in good, albeit luxuriant in euill: while as others are ſacrificing praiſe to God, they are ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crificing to Mammon, to their Nets, to their Bellies. A good man is as a good tree planted at the riuers of waters,<note place="margin">Pſal. 1.3.</note> and bringing forth good fruit in due ſeaſon, but theſe bring forth euill fruit at all ſea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons, and can finde no ſeaſon for good.<note place="margin">Luk. 13.<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
               </note>
            </p>
            <p>Thirdly, conſider how Chriſt Ieſus is opponed to theſe men, yea to all men: He is as the fruitfull Apple trée of the Garden, they as the barren trées of the Wood, no trée comparable to the Apple-trée, for pleaſantneſſe of the fruit there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of to the eye, to the ſmell, to the taſte, no trée like it, againſt thirſt, againſt hunger, againſt faintheartedneſſe and ſickneſſe. The Apples of this trée will baniſh hun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger, quench thirſt, and comfort the ſicke and languiſhing heart. Therefore the hungry, the thirſty and faint ſoule put<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teth vp a Petition to her Lord in the fifth Verſe, <hi>Stay me with Flagons,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Cant. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> 
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
               </note> 
               <hi>and comfort me with Apples, for I am ſicke of loue.</hi> In reſpect of theſe ſingular vertues hee is called the Trée of Life in the midſt of the Paradiſe of God,<note place="margin">Reu. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>
               </note> and in the midſt of the
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:173894:9"/> ſtréet of the new <hi>Ieruſalem,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Reu. 22.2.</note> bearing twelue manner of fruits euery month, and ſen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding forth leaues that heale the nations. Oh what a ſtore of meat and medicine is here! Oh what harueſts of comfortable fruits! twelue times twelue, that is, 144. harueſts of conſolations are brought out by this trée euery yeere. Here is abundance of medicine againſt the poiſon of the tree of knowledge, whereby our parents in Paradiſe brought death on themſelues, and their whole poſteritie. The fruit of that trée hath poiſoned vs all, no medicine can make vs whole, and frée vs of that poi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon, but only the fruit and leafe of this Apple-trée, this Trée of Life, Chriſt Ieſus.</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">Num. 21.8.</note>He is as the braſen Serpent: they that were ſtung with the fiery Scorpions could not bee cured but by looking vp to it, neither can we that are ſtung by that old Serpent be made whole, but by loo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king vp to Chriſt. He is as the waters of <hi>Iordan:</hi>
               <note place="margin">2. King. 5.12.</note> albeit <hi>Naaman</hi> in his carnall conceit once ſaid, are not <hi>Abanah</hi> and <hi>Pharpar,</hi> riuers of <hi>Damaſcus,</hi> better than all the waters of <hi>Iſrael?</hi> yet by experi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:173894:9"/> he found there was no curing of his Leproſie but by waſhing himſelfe in <hi>Ior<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dan:</hi> and if we contemne the bloud of Ie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſus,<note place="margin">Heb. 10.26.</note> there remaineth no more ſacrifice for our ſinnes. Of that Trée of Know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge God ſaid, <hi>If ye eate ye ſhall die.</hi> But of this Trée of life he ſaith,<note place="margin">Ioh. 6.53.</note> 
               <hi>Except yee eate, ye ſhall die.</hi> Wee eſteeme our Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rents fooles becauſe they did eat where God forbade to eat. There was medicine for eating of that Trée of Knowledge, but no medicine for no eating of this trée of Life. This trée although in the be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ginning it was but a little graffe ſpring<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing out of the roote of <hi>Ieſſe,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Iſa. 11.1.</note> yet being co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uered with earth (in the buriall) grew to a great Trée (in the reſurrection) the top whereof (in the Aſcenſion) grew in height aboue the Heauens, and (in the preaching of the Goſpell) ſent forth branches to the outmoſt ends of the earth,<note place="margin">Hoſ. 14.7.8.</note> that all Nations might reſt vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der his ſhadow, and enioy his comforta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble fruits to euerlaſting life: we can haue no life but from this Trée of Life. Thus concerning the propoſition: followeth the particular expoſition thereof, where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in is declared the effectuall working of
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:173894:10"/> the excellency of this Tree in the Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtian ſoule, it worketh deſire and delight. The reaſons of this ſoules deſire and de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>light are ſet downe three in number. Firſt, ſhe delighteth in this Trée, that ſhee may reſt and repoſe vnder it. Se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>condly, that ſhe may be couered with the ſhadow of it. Thirdly, that ſhe may eat the fruit of it, as being ſwéet to her taſte. Concerning the ſoules delight and deſire, conſider how that firſt ſhe ſpeakes of the excellency of this trée, and then of her de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſire toward it, and her delight in it. For it is not poſſible wee can haue a deſire of the Lord, or a delight in the Lord, except wee firſt know his excellency and good<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe. It is true concerning the naturall man, of naturall things vnknowne of him he hath no deſire, how much leſſe can ſpirituall things affect him, being vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>knowne of him? The men of this world miſregard the Lord, and thoſe things that belong to his Kingdome, becauſe they know them not.<note place="margin">Mat. 13.45, 46.</note> The Kingdome of Heauen is like a pearle of great price, which when a Merchant hath found, he ſelleth all that he hath, and buy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth it: He finding this pearle quitteth
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:173894:10"/> himſelfe of all things to gaine it, to get it; except he finde it and ſee it, hee labou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reth not to attaine vnto it, he careth for no more but this preſent life, becauſe he knoweth no better:<note place="margin">Mar. 8.34.</note> If the <hi>Gadarens</hi> had knowne Chriſt, they would not haue pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ferred their ſwine vnto him. The Lord Ieſus came vnto his owne people,<note place="margin">Ioh. 1.11.</note> the Iewes, but his owne receiued him not.<note place="margin">Mat. 27.20, 21. 1 Cor. 2.7.</note> Why? becauſe they knew him not: for if they had knowne him, they would not haue preferred a robber vnto him: if they had knowne him, they would not haue crucified that Lord of glory. The Lord ſaid to the woman of <hi>Samaria,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Ioh. 4.10.</note> If thou kneweſt the gift of God, thou wouldſt haue asked; ſhe asked not, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe ſhe knew not. No maruell to ſee the worldling haue little deſire of the Lord, haue little delight in him. What wonder he fixe his heart on the things of of this world onely, ſéeing he knoweth no better: for if he knew better he would do better. If theſe carnall and worldly min<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded men that were called to the wedding of the Kings Sonne,<note place="margin">Luk. 14.16.</note> had knowne how great a benefit they were inuited vnto, they would not haue refuſed to come.
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:173894:11"/> They would not haue preferred their farmes and Oxen, that is, their earthly commodities, they would not haue pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ferred their wiues, that is, their fleſhly pleaſures to that heauenly banquet. All tend to this, that we ſtriue to get a ſight of Chriſt,<note place="margin">Phil. 3.8.</note> that we ſtudy by all meanes to attaine to the excellency of the know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge of him, that our hearts may be ina<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moured with him, that he may become the Butte of our deſires, and only obiect of our delights. Secondly, as deſire muſt begin at knowledge, ſo knowledge muſt end in deſire: in vaine we heare of Chriſt, in vaine we know him, except our hearing and our knowledge ſet an edge on our de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſire, to affect him, to ſéeke him. When Ie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſus had ſhowne vnto the Iewes of the Bread of Life which came downe from Heauen to giue life to the world,<note place="margin">Io<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> 6.34.</note> their de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſire as ſtirred vp, openeth their mouth to ſay, <hi>Lord giue vs euermore that bread.</hi> What euer a man knoweth of Chriſt, he knoweth nothing as he ought to know,<note place="margin">1 Cor. 8.2.</note> ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cept he loue him as much as he knoweth him: if we acknowledge him to excell all other things, we muſt loue him and de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>light in him, wee muſt deſire him and
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:173894:11"/> require him aboue all other things.</p>
            <p>Now to the reaſon of the ſoules de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſire and delight. Firſt the wearied ſoule delighteth in this trée, that ſhe may ſit, that is, reſt, remaine, and repoſe her ſelfe vnder it: Chriſt is to be ſought and deſired for himſelfe, that we may reſt and remaine in him, that we may repoſe on him. And good reaſon haue we ſo to do if we conſider, either what he is, or what he hath, what the father hath pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſed of him, or what the Sonne hath promiſed of himſelfe. What is he? hee is <hi>Alpha</hi> and <hi>Omega,</hi> the firſt and the laſt.<note place="margin">Reu. 1.8. Rom. 11.36.</note> He is the laſt end of all ends, for to him are all things, therefore he is to be deſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red for himſelfe, and all other things for him. What euer we deſire beſide him, we are not to reſt vpon it, but muſt vſe it as a meane to further vs to this laſt end, this ſupreme good: and wee diſhonour him much, and diſaduantage our ſelues more, if we deſire or ſéeke him for any o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther thing beſide himſelfe, if we take in that laſt end of all things to be vſed as a meane and mids to any other thing. Se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>condly, we haue good reaſon to reſt on him if we conſider what he hath. He hath
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:173894:12"/> in himſelfe all perfection and beauty: he hath in himſelfe ſufficiency both for him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe and for vs,<note place="margin">Gen. 17.1.</note> as being <hi>El ſhaddai,</hi> God all-ſufficient.<note place="margin">Col. 1.19. Col. 2.9, 10 Ioh. 1.14.</note> It pleaſed the Father that all fulneſſe ſhould dwell in him, in him dwelleth all the fulneſſe of the Godhead bodily, in him we are compleat and full, he is full of grace and truth; fulneſſe of light, fulneſſe of life, fulneſſe of ſaluati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on is in him, and what good thing is to bée deſired which wee ſhall not finde in him? In him are hid all the treaſures of wiſdome and knowledge.<note place="margin">Col. 2.3.</note> He is made of the Father to be our wiſdome, iuſtifica<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion,<note place="margin">1. Cor. 1.30.</note> ſanctification, and redemption: are we fooles? in him we haue wiſdome: are wee guilty of ſinne and condemnation? in him we haue righteouſneſſe: are wee filthy and prophane? in him wee haue ſanctification: are we ſold vnder ſinne to hell?<note place="margin">Epheſ. 1.7.</note> in him we haue redemption, euen the remiſſion of our ſinnes in his bloud. Seeing then he hath all things we ſtand in need of, to frée vs from extreme miſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry, and to bring vs to ſupreme felicity, good reaſon haue wee to reſt and repoſe on him.</p>
            <p>Thirdly, what profeſſed the father of
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:173894:12"/> him? <hi>This is my beloued Son</hi> 
               <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>,<note place="margin">Mat. 17.5.</note> 
               <hi>in whom I am well pleaſed,</hi> on whom I haue reſted and repoſed. If the father hath reſted on him for fulneſſe of ſatiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>faction, why ſhould not we repoſe on him for fulneſſe of ſaluation? Laſtly, what hath he promiſed of himſelfe?<note place="margin">Mat. 11.29.</note> 
               <hi>In me yee ſhall finde reſt to your ſoules:</hi> Wée may with that rich man,<note place="margin">Luk. 12.19.</note> bid our ſoules reſt on our Barnes; but try who will, hée ſhall finde no true reſt but in Chriſt Ieſus. As for other things, the more we poſſeſſe them, the more they poſſeſſe vs, yea the more they oppreſſe vs; the more ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tained, the more they inflame the deſire: as water, the more it be drunke by a drop<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſie man, the more it kindleth his thirſt, and as oile powred on a fire, it is ſo farre from quenching that it increaſeth the flame. The reaſon is, firſt, becauſe there is no proportion betwixt the ſpirit of man and theſe things, it being eternall and heauenly, theſe being temporall and earthly. Secondly, becauſe nothing can reſt but in the owne place whence it hath its beginning, and on things ſutable to its nature: therefore ſtones, metals, and all earthly things thruſt vp in the
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:173894:13"/> aire, do not reſt till they returne to their originall earth againe, the center of their motion:<note place="margin">Iob. 5.7.</note> and hence it is, that a fiery flame is in a continuall reſtleſſe motion, &amp; ſhaking and ſhiuering, alwaies tending vpward toward its naturall place; euen ſo,<note place="margin">Eccl. 12.7.</note> the ſpirit of man which is from a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>boue, cannot reſt but on things aboue. The heart which God hath made for him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe, hath no reſt but on God himſelfe, as the Needle of a Mariners compaſſe can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not be ſtill and ſtedfaſt except it point di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rectly toward the Northerne ſtarre. O then, my ſoule, ſince in thy vnſtable and reſtleſſe motion, thou haſt wandred too long from thy Lord, ſéeking reſt elſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>where and haſt found none,<note place="margin">Pſal. 116.7.</note> 
               <hi>Returne to thy reſt my ſoule,</hi> the Lord is thy reſt, hée is the center that muſt ſtay thy vnſtable and reſtleſſe motion.</p>
            <p>This Doctrine confutes and reproues, Firſt, all Papiſts in generall. Secondly, politike Papiſts that dwell among vs in particular. Thirdly, vs all in vniuerſall, ſo farre as we are carnall and worldly minded. Hereby are conuinced all Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>piſts in generall that reſt not on Chriſt, that ſeeke not their perfection and ſalua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:173894:13"/> in him, but elſewhere they mixe the bloud of Chriſt with the bloud of Mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tyrs, his merits with theirs. They make many Mediators &amp; Sauiours beſide him, and ſo forſaking the Fountaine of liuing waters,<note place="margin">Ier. 2.13.</note> they dig vnto themſelues dry Ce<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſternes that can hold no water. Fulneſſe of ſaluation is only and wholly in Chriſt,<note place="margin">Col. 1.19.</note> wholy in him,<note place="margin">Col. 2.9.1<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
               </note> for it pleaſed the father that all fulnes ſhould be in him; in him we are compleat,<note place="margin">Heb. 7.25.</note> and he is able to ſaue perfectly them that come vnto God by him: only in him, for there is no ſaluation in another,<note place="margin">Act. 4.12.</note> and among men there is giuen no other name vnder Heauen, whereby we may be ſaued. He is as <hi>Noahs</hi> Arke, out of the which there was not ſafety; &amp; as <hi>Ia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cobs</hi> Ladder, by the which only we haue acceſſe to Heauen.<note place="margin">1 Cor. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>.13</note> Was <hi>Paul</hi> crucified for vs, or were we baptized in his name? Our Lord was crucified betweene two Theeues, not two Apoſtles; as for the A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſtles, one of them betrayed him, ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther of them denied him, the reſt with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>drew themſelues the time of his ſuffe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring, to ſhew that his bloud only is the price of our redemption, that he alone trod the Vinepreſſe of Gods wrath,<note place="margin">Iſa. 63.3.</note> and
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:173894:14"/> that of all the people there was none with him: this is the old faith, and there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore the only ſound Religion. Will we looke to <hi>Dauid</hi> the ſweet ſinger of <hi>Iſrael,</hi> a man according to Gods owne heart? will we follow either his practiſe or his precept? by both he teacheth vs this Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligion. Concerning his practiſe, he ſaith to the Lord,<note place="margin">Pſal. 23.25.</note> 
               <hi>Whom haue I in Heauen but thee? and on earth I haue deſired none with thee;</hi> and giuing a Precept he ſaith, <hi>Let Iſrael wait vpon the Lord,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Pſal. 130.7, 8.</note> 
               <hi>for with the Lord is the great redemption, and he will redeeme Iſrael from all his iniquities.</hi> Let other Nations wait on whom they pleaſe, let the <hi>Egyptians</hi> wait vpon their <hi>Iſis</hi> and <hi>Oſiris,</hi> let the <hi>Moabites</hi> and <hi>Midi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>anites</hi> wait vpon their <hi>Baalpeor,</hi> let the <hi>Amonites</hi> attend on <hi>Moloch,</hi> the <hi>Sidoni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ans</hi> on their <hi>Aſhtaroth,</hi> the <hi>Philiſtims</hi> on <hi>Dagon,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Ezek. <hi>22.3.</hi> Ge<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="3 letters">
                     <desc>•••</desc>
                  </gap>im. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap> 
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap>.</note> the <hi>Turkes</hi> on their <hi>Mahomet,</hi> the other Pagans on a thouſand other ſuch dirty gods of their owne inuention, and let the Papiſts as fondly doting on Idols, as they wait on as many ſuch gods of their owne creation, let all Idola<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters, I ſay, wait vpon their Idols, it be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>commeth the <hi>Iſrael</hi> of God, to wait on
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:173894:14"/> the God of <hi>Iſrael,</hi> it becommeth all true Chriſtians to wait on Chriſt their Lord, to reſt on him alone. He is <hi>Iacobs</hi> ſtone on which he reſted; they that reſt on this ſtone, ſhall finde with <hi>Iacob</hi> Heauen ope<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned, a ready paſſage to Heauen, and the Angels of God attending them, to fur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſh and further them in this way.</p>
            <p>Secondly, this Doctrine makes againſt politike Papiſts dwelling among vs, who make religion to ſerue their policie, &amp; take in Chriſt, the laſt and of all ends, to be a mids and meane to their crafty de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſignes: as many come to the muſters for feare of poynding, ſo theſe come with vs to the Church, to the Word and Sacra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment for feare of the Kings Law. They profeſſe the Goſpell of Chriſt with vs, that they may enioy their ſtate among vs, like <hi>Iudas</hi> that followed Chriſt for the bagge; a better purſe of mony will make <hi>Iudas</hi> betray his Maſter. <hi>Iupiter</hi> (ſay the heathen Prophets moralizing by fables) could not obtaine the loue of <hi>Da<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nae</hi> till he turned himſelfe in a ſhoure of gold: oh, but then ſhe kept him in her bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſome. If Chriſt were not turned in gold, he ſhould not be welcommed by theſe our
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:173894:15"/> ſymbolizing falſe brethren: if the Goſpell were not accompanied with ſecurity of eſtate, with profits, preferments, and o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther emoluments, they would not receiue it, they would not profeſſe it. This is not to reſt on Chriſt and his truth, but on theſe worldly emoluments, for the which they profeſſe Chriſt and his truth. Theſe men, as the meſſens of Mammon follow Chriſt, becauſe their maſter Mammon is in his company; but when Chriſt and Mammon ſhall part company, like <hi>De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mas</hi> they will leaue Chriſt and follow Mammon,<note place="margin">2 Tim. 4.10</note> and then the world ſhall ſee that not Chriſt but Mammon was their maſter. Who loue Chriſt, who ſeeke him, who follow him, muſt loue him, muſt ſeeke him, muſt follow him for himſelfe, otherwaies they doe not, no they cannot reſt vpon him.</p>
            <p>Laſtly, this Doctrine fighteth againſt the worldly-mindedneſſe of vs all, while as we ſeeke other things to leane vnto, and to reſt vpon beſide Chriſt: for euen <hi>Iſrael</hi> the people of God ſometimes be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſide God can leane to <hi>Egypt,</hi>
               <note place="margin">2. King. 18.<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>1.</note> a ſtaffe of reed, which breaking faileth them, and thruſteth through their hand. Whateuer
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:173894:15"/> we leane to beſide Chriſt, it is as a ſtaffe of reede, it helpeth not but hurteth. Is it wiſdome? is it learning? is it riches? is it friendſhip? Whatſoeuer a man truſteth vnto beſide the Lord, it ſhall diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>appoint him: in the end it ſhall proue not helpfull but hurtfull vnto him, as did <hi>Hamans</hi> honour, <hi>Goliahs</hi> greatneſſe,<note place="margin">Eſter. 7. 1 Sam. 17. 2 Sam. 17.</note> and <hi>Achitophels</hi> wiſdome. We muſt not loue the world then, nor yet the things of this world,<note place="margin">1 Cor. 7.31</note> for the ſhape of this world paſſeth away, and whatſoeuer is in the world, as the luſt of the fleſh,<note place="margin">1 Ioh. 2.16</note> the luſt of the eyes, and the pride of life, are not of the father, but of the world, and all things worldly are but vanity, paſſing as a ſmoke, as a dreame, as a ſhadow. Our Treaſure is not here, but aboue, here be only the ſhadowes of good things, their ſubſtance is in Heauen. We laugh at the fooliſhneſſe of little Babes when we ſée them chaſe ſhadowes, and glame after them on a Wall, with confidence to apprehend them. Greater fooles ſhall we proue if wee chaſe the things of this world, for they are but ſhadowes indéed. The pompe, the riches, and pleaſures of this world, they are but ſhadowes of
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:173894:16"/> that glory, riches and ioy that is hid with Chriſt in God. Good reaſon is it then we ſettle our minds and hearts on him, and not on any thing elſe: We muſt forſake all things to winne him,<note place="margin">Mat 1<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>.44</note> like that wiſe and thrifty Merchant, who finding that precious Treaſure in a field, ſold all that he had and bought it.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Vnder his ſhadow.</hi> The ſecond reaſon of the ſoules delight in this Trée, is the ſhadow of it. The ſhadow of a well buſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ked Trée ſerues for refreſhing of a wea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ried Traueller, it ſerues to couer him from the parching heate of the Sunne, and to ſaue him from a tempeſt. The ſhadow of Ieſus Chriſt refreſheth the wearied ſoule,<note place="margin">Ma<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>. 11.<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>8.</note> ſore trauelled vnder the burthen of ſinne, tentations and afflicti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons; it couereth him from the fiery heat of Gods conſuming wrath, it defendeth and holdeth off the tempeſt of his iudge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments.<note place="margin">Iſa. 32.18.</note> Vnder his ſhadow is that Taber<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nacle of peace,<note place="margin">Lam. 4.20.</note> that ſure Habitation and ſafe reſting place, in the which the Lord hath promiſed his people ſhall dwell and liue: Chriſt is our peace, our ſure habita<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion &amp; ſafe reſting place; if we dwell elſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>where, we can haue no peace, no ſurety,
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:173894:16"/> no refreſhment, we cannot liue vnder a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nother ſhadow, another ſhadow may ſlay thee, it cannot ſaue thée. <hi>Pliny</hi> in his <hi>Naturall Hiſtory</hi> writeth of the Taxus,<note place="margin">Plin. lib. <hi>16.</hi> cap. <hi>1<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>.</hi>
               </note> which we call the Yew trée, that in <hi>Arca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dia</hi> the ſhadow of it is ſo deadly and poi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſonable, that if a man ſléepe or eat vnder it, it doth preſently poyſon and kill him; ſuch is the ſhadow of any thing beſide Chriſt, it may well kill vs, it cannot kéepe vs, it is a Taxus to intoxicate and poy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon, not a ſauing ſhadow to comfort and refreſh. A ſhadow is made of a light and a body: where a darke body interuening betwéene and a light, obſcures the light, there is the ſhadow.<note place="margin">Col. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>.17</note> The Sacrifices and Ceremonies of the Law were ſhadowes of Chriſt, wherein the people did ſit, ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uing the light of the Goſpell eclipſed and obſcured to them, for then the wiſdome of God was a myſtery and hid. Then was the new Teſtament couered in the old,<note place="margin">1 Cor. 2.7. Eph. 3 5.</note> as the old is now diſcouered in the new. Now theſe ſhadowes are fled a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>way, ſince the day of ſaluation is brea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thed forth in the riſing of that Sunne of righteouſneſſe: Wée then that are not vnder the Law, muſt not deſire any more
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:173894:17"/> to ſit vnder theſe ſhadowes,<note place="margin">Luke 1.78.</note> ſince the day-ſpring hath viſited vs from on high. We haue better ſhadowes to ſit vnder: the firſt is the ſhadow of his fleſh and hu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>manity, through the which the glorious light of his Diuinity appeared,<note place="margin">Ioh. 1.14.</note> and was ſeene as the glory of the only begotten of the father, full of grace and truth. Vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der this ſhadow we muſt delight and ſit, in this ſhadow we muſt ſeeke for reſt, re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>freſhment and ſafety. It is the ſhadow of his fleſh whereby we are ſaued; no ſal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uation had béene to man, except God had become man, we ſhould haue had no com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fort againſt ſin, except in his fleſh he had borne our ſinnes; we could haue had no ſafety from the wrath of God,<note place="margin">Pſal. 19.9.</note> except he in his fleſh had borne it. But now our fleſh may reſt in hope,<note place="margin">Ioh. 1.14. Hoſ. 13.14.</note> becauſe the Word was made fleſh: now we may laugh at death and deſtruction, becauſe by his death he hath béene the death of Death, and hath ſaued vs from deſtruction. Oh! then let vs ſtill delight to ſit vnder this ſhadow of his fleſh and humanity, which if it had not interuened betwéene vs and God, in his wrath, as with a burning fire, we all ſhould haue béene conſumed.
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:173894:17"/> Bleſſed be his holy name for euer and e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer, for preparing ſuch a ſhadow to couer vs,<note place="margin">Pſal. 32.1.</note> and bleſſed are they for euer and euer who delight vnder this ſhadow, whereby in all their tribulations they are ſwéetly refreſhed, whereby all their iniquities are cloſely couered, and their ſoules are ſurely ſaued from the wrath to come.</p>
            <p>Neither is his fleſh only, but his Word and Sacraments alſo are his ſhadowes, vnder the which we muſt delight to ſit,<note place="margin">1. Cor. 13.12.</note> for as yet we ſée him not face to face, we ſée him not as he is, but in a mirror, and in a riddle or obſcure ſpéech, for what is to be knowne of God here by Word and Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>craments is nothing in reſpect of that we ſhall know hereafter,<note place="margin">1 Ioh. 3.2.</note> when wée ſhall ſée him as he is, and know him as wee are knowne of him: Therefore in this chap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter, verſe 9. hee is ſaid to ſpeake to vs through a wall, and to looke to vs thorow windowes and latteſſes. The Holy of holies was couered with a Vaile, which was rent in the ſuffring of our Lord, to ſhew that the myſteries of the Law were reuealed and diſcouered in Chriſt, and as the twi-light of the Law was darkneſſe in reſpect of the bright meridian Sun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhine
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:173894:18"/> of the Goſpell, ſo is this of the Goſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pell in reſpect of that which is to be re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uealed in the Kingdome of glory: euen now in this Kingdome of grace the Lord ſtandeth behind our wall, he ſpeaketh to vs through a veile, he looketh to vs tho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>row windowes and latteſſes: we ſée him in a mirrour, and in a riddle, we heare him ſpeake as it were behind a wall in his Word, we ſée him looke as it were thorow latteſſed windowes in the holy Sacraments. Theſe are all ſhadowes of Chriſt, in which we muſt delight to ſit for ſafe protection, and refreſhing conſolati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, till that glorious day breath forth his light, and then ſhall theſe ſhadowes flye away.<note place="margin">Ioſ 5.12.</note> Manna was the peoples food in the Wilderneſſe, and ceaſed when they came to <hi>Canaan:</hi> ſo by the Word and Sacraments we muſt be refreſhed here, till we come to Heauen our <hi>Canaan.</hi> But there doe ceaſe Word and Sacraments, which are but ſhadowes of things that be there, there ſhall be no vſe of the ſhadow, there ſhall we not ſée him in a mirror, but as he is; there ſhall we not heare him as behind a wall or veile, for all things that make partition betwixt vs and our Lord
<pb n="27" facs="tcp:173894:18"/> ſhall be taken away, there ſhall he ſpeake to vs mouth to mouth, there ſhall he not looke to vs thorow latteſſed windowes, but with a diſcouered face, and we ſhall be able to behold the glory of his face vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ueiled, albeit infinitely more glorious than the face of <hi>Moſes,</hi> when hee came downe from the Mount,<note place="margin">2 Cor. 3.7.</note> and could not be looked vpon for the brightneſſe of his countenance.<note place="margin">Reu. 21.22, 23.</note> In that heauenly Ieruſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lem ſhall bee no Temple, no Sunne, no Moone,<note place="margin">1 Cor. 15.28.</note> for the Lambe is the light there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of, he ſhall be all in all immediatly. But till that day breath forth his light, wee muſt not only content our ſelues, but al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſo delight our ſelues in theſe ſhadowes, for without them he giueth no preſence, we cannot heare him, nor ſee him but in them: except we delight to ſit in theſe ſha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dowes, his fleſh cannot ſhadow vs, his ſuffering in the fleſh cannot couer vs from the wrath to come. And this is the third reaſon of the ſoules delight in Chriſt, his ſwéet and comfortable fruits, which ſwéetneſſe the Church teſtifieth by her experience; His fruit was ſwéet to my taſte. Not onely doth this Trée in re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gard of the ſhadow ſerue for ſafegard and
<pb n="28" facs="tcp:173894:19"/> refreſhment, but in reſpect of the fruit, it ſerueth alſo to comfort the hungry &amp; thir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſty ſoule. The Lord promiſeth to thoſe that ſit vnder this Trée,<note place="margin">Iſa. 49.10.</note> that the burning heat of the Sun ſhall not ſmite them, and that they ſhall neither hunger nor thirſt. <hi>Iſrael</hi> in the Wilderneſſe had the cloud to couer them and Manna to eat: Chriſt is both to vs a Cloud to couer, and Manna to eat.<note place="margin">1 Cor. 10.3</note> Manna was a liuely Sacrament of Chriſt, and hence it is called a ſpiritu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>all food, amongſt other reſemblances it had of Chriſt, all manner of good taſtes were in it, <hi>Wiſd.</hi> 16.10. And ſo in Chriſt is euery thing deſirable, and euery thing delightfull, he hath the taſte of the Wine, <hi>Ioh.</hi> 15.1. the taſte of the Oliue, <hi>Rom.</hi> 11.17. the taſte of the hony and the hony combe, <hi>Cant.</hi> 4.11. the taſte and ſent of all delicate ſpices, <hi>ibid.</hi> 13, 14. As here he hath the taſte of the apple, yea of euery good Apple, for ſo the originall word <hi>Ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>puach</hi> here vſed doth ſignifie. And what I pray you elſe is meant hereby, but that he was anointed with the oyle of gladnes aboue his fellowes,<note place="margin">Pſal. 45.7.</note> 
               <note place="margin">Ioh. 3.34.</note> and that he receiued not the ſpirit by meaſure. In a word, that the graces and fruits of the ſpirit in
<pb n="29" facs="tcp:173894:19"/> him for vs are of infinite variety and va<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lue, for by him we haue righteouſneſſe, peace and ioy of the holy Ghoſt, <hi>Rom.</hi> 14.17. He is made by the father vnto vs, our wiſdome, iuſtification,<note place="margin">1 Cor. 1.30</note> ſanctification and redemption. By him wee are made the righteouſneſſe of God.<note place="margin">2 Cor. 5.21 Col. 1.20.</note> By the bloud of his Croſſe all things are pacified both in Heauen and Earth.<note place="margin">ibid. 21, 21.</note> By the body of his fleſh we are reconciled. By his bloud we haue redemption, euen the remiſſion of our ſinnes.<note place="margin">Epheſ. 1.7. Ephe. 2.13. Iſa. 53.5. 2 Tim. 1.10</note> By his bloud we that were farre off are made neere. By his ſtripes we are made whole. By his death, death is deſtroyed, and life is brought to light. By his death he hath deſtroyed him who had the power of death; that is, the De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uill,<note place="margin">Heb. 2.14, 15. Eph. 2.15. Gal. 3.</note> and we are deliuered from the feare and bondage of death. By his fleſh is ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken away the diuiſion and ſeparation be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>twixt God and vs. By his curſe we are ſaued from the malediction of the Law. By his pouerty wee are made rich.<note place="margin">2 Cor. 8. Eph. 2.</note> By his condemnation wee are iuſtified.<note place="margin">Eph. 2.</note> By his death we haue life. He is our peace. He is our aduocate with the father,<note place="margin">1 Ioh. 2. 1 Ioh.</note> and a propitiation for our ſinnes. He taketh away the ſinnes of the world. He ſaueth
<pb n="30" facs="tcp:173894:20"/> vs his people from our ſinnes. He hath torne in péeces the obligation that was againſt vs.<note place="margin">Matth. 1.</note> 
               <note place="margin">Col. 2.</note> He iuſtifieth the wicked by faith.<note place="margin">Rom. 4. Rom. 5.1.</note> By him we are at peace with God. By him wee haue boldneſſe with confi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dence to draw néere to God.<note place="margin">Epheſ. 3.12.</note>
            </p>
            <p>In a word, he hath all manner of delecta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble &amp; good taſtes, all things that are to be deſired are to be ſound in him,<note place="margin">Col. 2.10.</note> and in him we are compleat. O admirable Trée that ſo aboundeth with ſuch fruits! O happy ſoule that taſteth, and thriſe happy ſoule that inioyeth the ſwéetneſſe of theſe fruits! Swéet ſo my taſte. Some things be ſwéet of their owne nature, and in themſelues,<note place="margin">Iudg. 14.18.</note> as is hony, according to that of <hi>Samſons</hi> riddle, What is ſwéeter than Hony? Some things are ſwéet to the taſte and mouth, which in themſelues haue no naturall ſwéetneſſe, for to the hungry ſoule, euen bitter things ſéeme ſweet; hunger is a ſauce that maketh them ſauory. The fruits of this Trée are moſt ſwéet in themſelues, yet not to eue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry taſte, not to the taſte that is preoccupi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed and vitiat with the ſent of fleſhly de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lights. The humour poſſeſſing the taſte ſuffereth not the ſwéetneſſe of theſe ſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rituall
<pb n="31" facs="tcp:173894:20"/> fruits to enter &amp; affect. As to thoſe that are in an Ague, the bitter humour that infects their taſte, maketh the ſwée<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teſt and healthſomeſt things diſtaſtfull and vnſauory:<note place="margin">1 Ioh. 2.5.</note> So the heart poſſeſſed with the loue of the world, cannot be af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fected toward God; things ſpirituall are abominable and diſtaſtfull to it. The na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turall man giuen ouer to ſinfull and fleſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly delights, perceiueth not the things that are of the ſpirit of God,<note place="margin">1 Cor. 1.14</note> for they are inſipide and vnſauory to him; neither can he perceiue them, for they are ſpiritually diſcerned: as none can diſcerne naturall things but by a naturall ſoule, ſo ſpiri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tuall things cannot be diſcerned but by a ſupernaturall ſpirit. His fruits are ſwéet to my taſte, ſaith the Bride. The Spouſe of Chriſt hath the Spirit of Chriſt, there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore ſhe can diſcerne things belonging to his Kingdome: and as they are moſt ſwéet in themſelues, ſo are they to her taſte. Hence we may diſcerne our ſelues; if we haue the Spirit of Chriſt, we will ſauour the things of the Spirit,<note place="margin">Rom. 8.</note> they will be moſt ſwéet and ſauory to our taſte, o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>therwaies we are ſenſuall, naturall and carnall, the ſupreme faculty in vs is a na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turall
<pb n="32" facs="tcp:173894:21"/> ſoule: for is not the life of euery liuing thing diſcerned by the operation thereof, it being proportionable to the obiect affected by it? the herbes of the field thirſt for the ſap of the earth, and the dew of Heauen, whereby they are nouriſhed and increaſed: whereupon we conclude that they haue a naturall life. The beaſts of the earth are affected toward things ſenſible, and by their ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>petite are carried toward thoſe things that be pleaſant to their ſenſe: Where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>upon we conclude, they haue alſo a ſenſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble life. And men without God affect things not only by nature and ſenſe, but alſo by reaſon: Whereupon wee con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clude, that they haue a reaſonable ſoule. And whereas many,<note place="margin">Mat. 6.32.</note> howbeit profeſſed Chriſtians, are affected and inclined only to things naturall, ſenſuall, and ſuch as are founded on reaſon, what can we con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clude of them, but that they liue a life on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly naturall, as do plants; ſenſuall, as do beaſts; and reaſonable, as do the heathen, and haue no ſpirituall life at all. Seeing their appetite doth not carry them to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward the things of God,<note place="margin">Col. 3.1.</note> it is certaine they liue not the life of God;<note place="margin">Rom. 8.5.</note> and (pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſe
<pb n="33" facs="tcp:173894:21"/> what they will) Chriſt liueth not in them by his Spirit, otherwaies their de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſire would be towards him, their delight would bee in him, and his fruits would be ſwéet to their taſte.</p>
            <p>Let vs ſtudy then to know our owne mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſery, &amp; Ieſus Chriſt his excellency; then our deſire and languor will bee toward him, our delight will bee in him. The ſoule that is weary of the burthen of ſinne, will hunger and thirſt after his righteouſneſſe, will earneſtly deſire to reſt and repoſe vnder his ſhadow. The Spirit that feeleth the piercing Arrowes of Gods wrath for ſinne, will aboue all things ſeeke to bee couered with the ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uing ſhadow of his mercy. O how ſweet will his comfortable fruits be to the hun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gry and diſtreſſed ſoule, that ſeeth no life, no refreſhment, no conſolation, but in him and through him!</p>
            <p>Now the Lord of life, that Father of mercies and God of all conſolation, ſo moue vs, ſo direct vs, ſo affect vs, that a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>boue all things we may ſeeke him, and finde him, to his euerlaſting glory, and our eternall felicity, <hi>Amen.</hi>
            </p>
         </div>
         <div type="prayer">
            <pb facs="tcp:173894:22"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:173894:22"/>
            <head>A ſweet and heauenly Prayer made for the helpe and direction of the weaker ſort of Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtians in knowledge, and comfor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>table <hi>alſo for the ſtronger.</hi>
            </head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">O</seg> Lord God, moſt glorious and mercifull, who ſearcheſt the hearts and knoweſt the thoughts of the ſonnes of men, wee thy vnworthy ſeruants doe here at this preſent moſt humbly preſent our ſelues before thee, aſhamed and grie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued for our manifold ſins committed againſt thee: Lord if thou ſhouldſt enter into iudgement with vs accor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding to our deſeruings, wee were not able to abide it, if thou (O GOD) ſhouldſt ſtrictly marke wherein the
<pb facs="tcp:173894:23"/> beſt of vs all haue erred before thee, O Lord, who were able to endure it? for we are loath ſome, leprous, and out of meaſure ſinfull: our minds ſo blinded, that we know nothing that may make for our bliſſe: our iudgements ſo ſhallow, that we cannot conceiue and rightly adiudge of holy and heauenly things: our memories ſo dull and dead, that wee can hold no good thought or holy meditation: our hearts ſo hardned, that neither thy mercies nor iudgements can bring vs to obedience: our wills ſo peruerted, that wee freely deſire nothing but e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uill: our affections ſo corrupted, that we luſt for and delight in nothing but wickedneſſe: our words ſo vaine and our workes ſo vile, that wee practiſe daily nothing but ſinfull rebellion a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt thee: Lord therefore for Ieſus Chriſt his ſake bee mercifull vnto vs thus miſerable ſinners: wee are weary of theſe our ſinfull conditions, and la<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>den
<pb facs="tcp:173894:23"/> with theſe our damnable abomi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nations, Lord be thou our refreſhing.</p>
            <p>Perſwade our hearts (deare God) by faith, that our ſinnes are forgiuen vs, our ſoules reconciled vnto thee, and our names written in the booke of life: we are inſtant ſuters vnto thee for this thy mercy, as was <hi>Moſes</hi> vpon the Mount, Lord ſhew vs thy glory, and ſay vnto our amazed ſoules, that thou art our ſaluation.</p>
            <p>And we moſt humbly beſeech thee to ſanctifie vs all with thy holy and heauenly feare, let thy Word and Spi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit dwell in vs in all wiſdome plente<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ouſly, that thereby our vile affections may be purified, our wicked minds renued, and our ſinfull liues moſt gra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciouſly amended, that as formerly we haue giuen our ſelues to prophane<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe, ſo euer hereafter we may apply our ſelues to holineſſe: O that our waies were made ſo direct, that euer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>laſtingly we may keepe they comman<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dements:
<pb facs="tcp:173894:24"/> O that wee could doe thy will on earth, as thine Angels and glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rified ſoules doe it in Heauen.</p>
            <p>Lord bleſſe with vs all thy Church and choſen, bleſſe this ſinfull nation, bleſſe all our friends and kindred, bleſſe this houſe and family, bleſſe all afflicted members, eſpecially ſuch as are wounded in conſcience for their ſinnes, continue thy bleſſed Goſpell vnto vs, and make vs truly thankfull for all thy mercies.</p>
            <p>And this night (wee beſeech thee) redouble thy bleſſings vpon vs that are humbled in prayer before thee, bleſſe vs in body, bleſſe vs in ſoule, bleſſe vs in the basket, bleſſe vs in the ſtore, bleſſe vs in whatſoeuer belong vnto vs within doores and with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out: giue vnto our bodies a comfor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>table reſt and ſleepe, pitch thine Angels about our tents, that nothing may deſtroy them, and keepe our ſoules from ſleeping in ſinne and the
<pb facs="tcp:173894:24"/> ſeducings of Satan: that wee (being bleſſed of thee in ſoule and body in this world) may haue the ſurer hope and truer hold of euerlaſting ſaluation from thee at that ſcreeching day of iudgement to come: and that for Ieſus Chriſt his ſake, who (we hope) at this preſent intercedeth to thee for vs, for a proſperous bleſſing from thee vpon vs, to whom with thee and thy holy ſpirit (three perſons, but one God) we deſire to returne all glory, honour, do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>minion, and thankſgiuing, this night and euerlaſtingly to come, both here on earth, and hereafter hope<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fully in Heauen. <hi>Amen.</hi>
            </p>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
